A Finding Aid to the Fred Mitchell Papers, 1938-2007, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Subject Files, 1943-2007; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 6 Linear feet Boxes 6-12
  - Kingsborough Community College, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Painting Course, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Spring 1995 Crisis, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Student Papers, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Watercolor Course, 1988-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 37-42)
    - College Art Gallery, "Fred Mitchell Paintings" (1987 February 4-1987 February 23), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - College Art Gallery, "Painting in Watercolor" (1992 December 2 -- 1993 January 5), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Franz Kline Show, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Administrative Matters, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Catalogue, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - "Franz Kline: The Early Works as Signals," University Art Gallery, SUNY Binghamton (1977 March 14 -- 1977 April 18), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Lecture, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Loans, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - My Writings and Notes, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Neuberger Museum, SUNY Purchase (1977), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Notes, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Possibilities and Plans, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Research, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Binder 9, Folder 55)
    - Sordoni Art Gallery, Wilkes College, Wilkes-Barre, PA (1978 August 18 - 1978 September 10), 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - University of Iowa Proposal for Retropsective Exhibition, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Landmark Gallery Exhibition "Fred Mitchell" (1982 January 9 -- 1982 February 3), 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Lattimore, Richmond, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Lee, Harry, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Leger, Fernand, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Loans, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Low, Terry, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "The Magic Circle," The Bronx Museum of the Arts (1977), 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Malevich, Kazimir, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Marceau, Marcel, 1973-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Markey Mark, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Manguet, Albert, undated; 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Marshall, John, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - McCabe, Tommy ("Tomassino"), 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - McCauley, Billy Ray, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - McLellan, Alden and Family, undated; 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - McNeil, George, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - McQuade, James M., 1970s-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17-18)
  - Meridian Community College Exhibition, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Meridian Museum of Art, 1972-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Missing Paintings and Objects, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Missing Tryptich, Middy the Juggler, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Mississippi, undated; 1960s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Mississippi Art Colony, 1960s-1990s; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 videocassette: VHS (Box 10, Folder 24-25)
  - Mississippi Museum of Art, Jackson, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Missouri Exhibitions, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - "Modernism into Abstraction: Fred Mitchell, 1940-1949" (2007 March), Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Moore, Frank, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Moore, Tom and Meridian, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Mosaics, 1956; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Motherwell, Robert, 1978-1994; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute of Art, 1990-2003; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor School of Art, Visiting Artist, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Nevelson, Louise, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - New Places and Needs, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - The New York School, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - New York University, 1963-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Newman, Annalee, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - "Nine Artists/Coenties Slip," Whitney Museum of American Art (1974), Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Normal, Craig, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Ochman, Jim, 1978-1983; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
  - Okada, Frank, 1963-2000; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Oregon Friends, 1985; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Outdoor Color Drawing Class, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Pace Gallery, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Pace, Stephen, 1970s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Painting Trip, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Passlof, Pat, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Pederson, Allen, 1977-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Pederson-Krag, Gillian, undated; 1970s-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Petrochi, Lello, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Pets -- Gwendolyn's Family,Vernoica, Euripidosia, Billy Budd, and Nikko-San, undated; 1984-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Pfriem, Bernard, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Piper, John, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Poets, undated; 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Poleski, Stephen, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Positano, Sigmund, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - Prefontaine, Steve, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Pribble, Easton, 1974-2001; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Pricing of Works of Art, 1976-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Queens College, 1973-1981; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Ramirez, Carlos, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations -- Letters from Special Friends, Usually in Reference to Exhibitions or Expectations, 1952-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations and References, 1980-1986; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Reeves, Paul, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Reproduction of Paintings, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Restoration of Paintings, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Reunions, Meridian High School and Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1992; 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Reviews, undated; 1950s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Reyher, Tobias, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Rich, Garry, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Rogers, George, 1960; 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Roko Gallery, Ithaca, New York, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Rooney, Peter ("Petrus"), undated; 1958-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Ruddick, Gary, 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Sager, Chris and Family, undated; 1966-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Selmowitz, Abram, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Schloss, Edith, 1970s-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Schmit, Gladys, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Schuyler, James, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Sepeshy, Zoltan, undated; 1960-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Silvermine Lecture, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Irene, undated; 1985-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Sokolowski, Linda, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Stamos, Theodoros, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- Fred Mitchell Exhibition (1993 November 12 - 1993 November 29), Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- Teaching, undated; 1975-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- University Art Gallery, Acting Director, 1967-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - State University of New York, New Paltz, undated; 1978-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - State University of New York, Stony Brook, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Stevens, John W. ("Dicky"), 1965-1994; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 32-33)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Stonewall, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Strauss, Jonathan and Beth, in Alaska, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Streeter, Middy, 1976-1983; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Strickland, John ("Giovanni"), 1964-1987; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Sultz, Phil and Family, 1956-2006; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 39-42)
  - Tabakman Gallery, "Group Show 1999" (1999 January 5-1999 January 31), 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The Tanager Gallery, 1983; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Tenth Street Days: The Co-ops of the 50's" (1977 December 20 -- 1978 January 7), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bob Tomlinson Gallery, undated; 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Tormented," Part I, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Universal Limited Art Editions, Inc., 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - University of Maine, Machias, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - University of North Carolina, Greensboro, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - University of Oregon, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
  - Venice, 1965-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 11-13)
  - Vicente, Esteban, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Mark Vinson and Fred Mitchell Solo Exhibitions, White Box Gallery (1997 November 7 -- 1997 November 29), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Ward, Jeffrey, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Ward, Sandra, undated; 1972-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Waring, Jimmy, 1963-1978; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Watercolor Painting, 1960s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - West Broadway Gallery, "Heart Attack" (1994 February 1 -- 1994 March 15), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - White, Ed, 1956; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Windley, Carlyle, 1969-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Winn, Kitty, 1970s-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Wisconsin State University Platteville, 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Wise, Barbi and Howard, undated; 1959-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Howard Wise Gallery, 1954-1965; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Wittgenstein, Ludwig - The Duty of Genius by Ray Monk, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Wojnarowicz, Daniel, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Wong, Martin, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Yeomans, Marion, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Zogbaum, Rufus, undated; 1973-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 31)
- Artwork, circa 1940s-2002; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 12-13
  Artwork by Mitchell consists mainly of drawings and sketches in ink and pencil. Many identified and dated. Some were done while traveling and others are studies for paintings. Also found are 4 abstract watercolors. Artwork by others includes drawings in pencil, ink, pastels and watercolors by Peter Rooney, students, and unidentified artists.
  Artwork by Mitchell is arranged by medium and filed alphabetically by folder title; artwork by others in arranged in the same manner.
  - By Mitchell, Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
    - Drawings, undated; circa 1940s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 32-41)
    - Drawings, Andrew, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - Drawings, All the Way Across II, Flying Westward, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Drawings, Around 57th Street, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Drawings, Buddhist Fresco, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - Drawings, Hawaii, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Drawings, Italy, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 47)
    - Drawings, Middy Triptych Studies, 1990-1992; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 48)
    - Drawings, Northern-Edging, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Drawings, Out into Space We Go, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Binder 13, Folder 2)
    - Drawings, The Pantheon, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Drawings, Remotion, undated; 1981-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Drawings, Sojourning, 1964; 1980; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Drawings, Spirit of Zattere, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Drawings, Story Illustrations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Drawings, Triptych Possibilities, 1990-1992; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Watercolors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - By Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
    - Drawings by Peter Rooney, 1972-1982; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Drawings by Unidentified Artists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Watercolors by Students and Unidentified Artists, 1987-1984; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Sketchbooks, 1955-1993; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 13, 15
  The series consists of 16 sketchbooks containing sketches and drawings in pencil, ink, and marker; a few are embellished with color. In addition, there are a small number of finished watercolors and one pastel. Subjects include figures, portraits, landscapes, harbor views, birds, and abstract compositions. Many sketches and drawings are identified and dated.
  Volumes are numbered chronologically. Many volumes represent a single year. However, some years filled more than one volume, a few volumes include several years, and some contain overlapping dates.
  - Volume 1, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Volume 2, "'Portrait of a Queen,' also Julie Morris on TV", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Volume 3 and Volume 4, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Volume 5, "Chenango, Binghamton, Susquehanna", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Volume 6, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Volume 7, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Volume 8, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Volume 9 and Volume 10, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Volume 11, Anatomical Studies, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key; Oversized material housed in Box 15 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Volume 12, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Volume 13, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Binder 13, Folder 23, Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Volume 14, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Volume 15, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Volume 16, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Sketchbook, Volume 11, Anatomical Studies (from Box 13, Folder 23), 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 15)
- Printed Material, 1938-2004; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
  This series includes a wide variety of printed material about or mentioning Mitchell, concerning friends, general art topics and other subjects of interest to him. Included are exhibition catalogs and announcements, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, promotional material from organizations, and concert programs.
  Printed material is arranged in rough chronological order. Additional printed material is enclosed with correspondence (Series 2), loose letters are found in some diaries (Series 4), and many subject files (Series 5) include significant amounts of printed material.
  - Printed Material, 1938-1960s; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 27-31)
  - Printed Material, 1970s-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1-9)
- Photographs, 1940s-2002; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 14
  Photographs of Fred Mitchell include portraits and candid views; he also appears with friends, students, and family members. There are images of his siblings and their respective families, as well as of Don Wright and unidentified individuals. Artwork documented in this series is mainly by Mitchell; also, there are photographs of works by Lois Dodd, William Freed, Hans Hofmann, George Preston, and Philip Sultz. Views of exhibition installations and openings record some of Fred Mitchell's solo exhibitions; views of group shows include some in which his sister, Elizabeth Pajerski, participated. Pictures of places include travel photographs.
  Photographs are categorized by subject - people, artwork, exhibition installations and openings, and places - and within each group, arrangement is alphabetical. Additional photographs are enclosed with correspondence (Series 2) and are included in many subject files (Series 5).
  - People, Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    - Fred Mitchell, 1940s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - Fred Mitchell at Art Students League (Eben Thompson, photographer), circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Fred Mitchell with Others, undated; 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Mitchell Family (Mother, Fred, Robert Lyle, Elizabeth), undated; 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Thomas Lyle Mitchell and Family (Marie, Tommy, Jimmy), 1950s-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Elizabeth Mitchell Pajerski and Family (Fred, Frank), undated, 1958-1995, Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Don Wright and Unidentified Individuals, undated; 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Artwork by Mitchell, Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    - Paintings, 1961-1989; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Paintings owned by Harold, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Sculpture, 1960; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 20-21)
    - Watercolors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Watercolors, Southern Tip Series, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Artwork by Others (executed 1950s-1980s), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Installations and Openings, Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    - Horne-Marshall Gallery, Meridian, Mississippi, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Lincoln Center Show, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Thomas McCormick Gallery, Chicago, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - White Box Gallery, Philadelphia, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified Venues, 1997; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Places, Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    - Hawaii Trip with Sandra Ward, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Italy -- Fiesole, Positano, Rome and Venice, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Old Mitchell Homestead, Ellistown, Mississippi, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - View from Ferry, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 33)
      Note on envelope indicates "Photograph from the ferry made by Beth in June of '86 --the Southern Tip School of Art"
    - Wall-South Neighborhood just Before Destruction of my Studio, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified, undated; 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 35)